[Music]
foreign
automation tutorial
as you all know I've already published
13 YouTube videos
covering different concepts of
tricentious Tasker latest version 16.
this is our 14th lesson where I'm gonna
teach you
how can we use libraries
and reusable test blocks while
automating your test cases by using
latest version Tyson test Tasker 16.
I would recommend you guys to please
visit my previous videos before you
watch this session
which will be helpful for you to
understand the concepts better way
please do subscribe to the channel click
on Bell icon you'll receive
notifications whenever I publish more
videos
thank you
okay so what is our agenda item
so libraries and reusable tester blocks
so what is Library so in Tasker library
is called as test clip Library test step
Library
okay
so why do we need this test step
libraries
see when you are automating or when you
are executing multiple test cases
there will be lot of steps or series of
steps sequence of steps that you will be
reusing
while automating your test cases
so let's assume in our previous session
we automated
the
shopping
cost shopping cart right where we
validated all the prices
including total price of your order
but
in that particular test case we have
used credit card as a payment method
what if
I want to use a payment method as check
or money order what happens your total
cost will be changed because there will
be additional payment method fee that
will be applied
so that means whatever the test case
that you automated earlier
has to be modified
but there are a lot of steps that are
same logging in is same
and then order blue jeans is same
checkout process is same but while
checking out you are changing the
payment method and while verifying the
prices you need to verify some
additional fees so there are two steps
that is that are changing but rest all
same
so in that case
you need not to recreate entire test
case or you need not to automate entire
test case
you just need to create Library
where you can store reusable steps
and the benefit is that whenever you
want to use or reuse those reusable
steps you can simply drag and drop into
the your test case
and what is reusable tester block
the steps inside the Library are called
reusable desktop blocks
so these steps can be reused throughout
multiple test cases once you identify
reusable tested blocks and drag and drop
them into Library you can reuse them
throughout multiple test cases
and libraries can contain any number of
reusable test blocks okay so I'm gonna
teach you how to create libraries and
how to reuse these tester blogs
shortly by using Tasker okay
so what I am going to teach you I'm
gonna teach you
creation of a new test case using
reusable tester blocks
and we are going to automate the new
test case with these reusable tester
blocks
and also I'm gonna teach you how to
modify a reusable test block reference
using resolve reference method
so whenever you want to modify your
usable test block
you cannot simply modify because if you
modify the reusable test block it is
going to modify all the test cases
that's why you need to resolve the
reference and then do modification
so now let's jump onto the system and
see how can we
automate a new test Case by using
library and then by using reusable test
blocks
okay so this is my Tasker 16.
so before we discuss about
libraries and reusable test blogs and
before we use these concepts by
automating one of the test case let's
understand what is the test case that we
automated in our previous session so if
you remember in my previous session what
we did we have validated the shipping
cost how
see we logged into
our webshop demo webshop and then went
to appearance and shoes
and then click on blue jeans and here we
added the quantity of 25 correct and we
added to cart
go to shopping cart
agree to the terms click on checkout
and here
in checkout process we entered billing
address
shipping address
we selected shipping method as ground
and here payment method we selected as a
credit card
so now let's assume if I want to
automate
the test case
where I need to use the payment method
as check our money order instead of
credit card
check our money order right so earlier
we selected credit card click that
continue
and then you provide your credit card
name
right you provide your credit so the
credit card holder name and card number
and the expiration date and click on
continue right so here any card number
that okay let's let's click on let's go
to card number okay let's provide the
card number also to understand properly
okay checkout process
and here we provided credit card number
so basically the credit card information
we provided let's take the credit card
number here
okay we provide the credit card number
here and then provide your code and
click on continue
so when you click on continue here the
charges whatever it is displaying it is
based on credit card
what if I select the payment method as
check our money order then you will have
some additional fee if I pay by using
check our money order let's go back here
let's change to check money order
continue here the payment information is
changed now you need not to provide your
credit card details instead you will you
will have a simple statement here I need
to validate the statement and go to
continue here if you see there is some
additional fee called payment method
additional fee because I used check our
money order so whenever I use check our
money order I want to validate the
the prices additionally this payment
method
apart from your subtotal and shipping
earlier we validated only subtotal and
shipping correct but now you will have a
payment method also so that means the
prices will change based on the payment
method that you enter
so now if I want to automate the
end-to-end test case
to validate the prices of your entire
shopping when you select money order
then what is the approach I need to take
I already automated the test cases of
credit card now I I need to automate the
test case of money order okay so if you
see here this is the test case that we
automated by using credit card
now I need to want automate another test
case with money order so what is the
approach that we need to take
so that is where the libraries and
reusable touch step blocks comes into
picture because
when you are changing your payment
method right the all the steps that we
follow
like login
is same
going to a parental tube is Operation
shoes is same
adding your
blue jeans is same
go to shipping cart that is also saying
agreeing to the terms that is also same
in this test case
click on checkout it is same providing
billing address same
right shipping method so he is also same
payment method is different
so that means
there are a lot of reusable steps that
are involved in automating this this
test case I need there are two methods
either I can simply copy this test case
entire test case
and create a duplication and do some
modifications
but which is not recommended because if
there is any change in your properties
you have to change in both the test
cases
so better use libraries test step
libraries provided by task okay so now
what is our first step
that we need to follow before we
automate
check-in money order scenario first step
is identify the reusable test tips
that you can reuse while automating the
new test case right so
for that go to in work
right click and create a library create
test step Library as I told you
libraries
is called as desktop library in task
click on create desktop Library
okay I created test step Library under
in work okay now we need to identify a
reusable steps
and
map those reusable test tips under
Library
as a reusable test step blocks how I'll
tell you let's assume this precondition
right this entire precondition where you
are opening URL logging in sorry
navigate to login page and providing
credentials this step can be reused as
it is in our new scenario
by using money order correct so that
means you can simply this entire folder
can drag and drop to library
so she observed clearly as soon as I
drag and drop to library what happens
this precondition see if you see here
this entire folder now is marked with
arrow mark
and a suffix with references included
that means
and here if you see the precondition is
error this is a reusable test step block
this is a reusable tester block
okay and this precondition is reference
of this reusable test block from the
library okay done post condition in post
condition also what are you doing order
success you are
uh once order is successful you are
clicking on continue and then you are
logging out
and wait until login is appear and
closing the browser so this is also
common in the test case so that means
this is also a reusable tested block
that means I can
now Mark this as a reusable testing
block so that's why drag and drop this
also into Library
now you see this turned into Arrow Mark
and there is a suffix with reference
precondition okay
and expand this process now expand this
process
and here
let me drag and drop order product
so that means ordering a product is
common
for our new test case also so that means
this is also a reusable function drag
and drop to your library
so as soon as I drag and drop here see
the reference is added
if you see here the reference is added
for the order product
done and start checkout process even
start checkout process is common
so this is also reusable function drag
and drop here
so done start checkout references built
and your start checkout process is
identified as a reusable tested block
under Library folder and
verification of prices is not reusable
function
sorry let me do one thing let me drag
and drop all the processes let's assume
that I identify this as a reusable
function verification of prices
check out also let's drag and drop
checkout also
and let's drag and drop confirmation
also
and drag and drop verification of
success
so Frankly Speaking this checkout
process and verification of prices are
not same in our case because in the
checkout process payment method is going
to change
and in the verification of prices the
prices that displays on the screen also
gonna change that means this is also not
reusable function
but confirmation is same as soon as I
confirm validation of
confirmation message is same so that is
reusable tester block and verification
of success also same that is also
reusable test block except start
checkout process accept checkout process
rest all same correct
so
checkout process and verification of
prices are not same but still I
identified them as reusable functions
I'll tell you why okay for now
I identified all the reusable tested
blocks and if You observe clearly
the library is not ordered in the
sequence of your execution
it is ordered based on your alphabetic
okay that's how it works in Tasker all
the tested blocks will be ordered in
alphabetic order okay so now done so we
identified reusable test step blocks
now let's create a new test case for the
new scenario let's automate
the new scenario no okay for that in in
work item
let me create a new test case here okay
the new test case right click
create
folder first
name this as session 14
Library
and
reusable
test steps okay test step blocks okay
so done
and here now
let's expand this okay let's keep this
expand this here okay
so now
in session 14 Library reusable test
blocks now I want to automate the
scenario what I told you know okay
logging in
order representation shoes but use the
payment method money order right how we
already automated everything
if you see we already identified all the
reusable Twisted blocks
so what is my first tip my first step is
logging in open URL login that means the
precondition whatever we automated here
I can reuse as it is
so for that this is my test case correct
this is my test case
this is my new folder this case let me
create a new test case here okay let me
create a new test case here create test
case
just mention this as
shipping
costs
money order this time it's not credit
card money order so now
first precondition where open URL
navigate login provide credentials is I
can reuse as it is so that's why I'm
gonna drag and drop this entire folder
to the test case
okay if you see here still you can see
the reference that means this
precondition is coming from your library
reference
okay done I logged in I automated login
functionality that's it for the new test
case as soon as I log in post condition
this also I can directly reuse logout
functionality also I just drag and drop
here
now
let's create a process folder here let
me create another folder
right click
create folder
process
so I am creating a folder and just
ordering it as process okay
under process now
I cannot re I can reuse lot of functions
order product I can directly drag and
drop order product
because ordering product is same
because go to operation choose and Order
and then start checkout this also I can
directly use that's why drag your
reusable tested block start checkout
reusable tested block from library and
drop into process folder
done and then check out process
actually the checkout process is going
to change little bit this checkout
process but still
what it is going to change the change is
in the checkout process your payment
method whatever you are gonna use
the payment method right instead of
credit card we'll be using money order
and here I'm not going to provide entire
credit card information but instead I'm
gonna just click on continue on the
screen okay this is gonna change okay
let's keep this aside info now
and what about next verification of
price is also not gonna change that's
why I don't want to drag that
and what about confirmation so
confirmation is same
just drag and drop here from library to
the new test case
and then verification of success also
same
so verification of success drag and drop
to the new process
done one two three four five six total
six steps out of six we only
built four steps now
checkout process so what I want to do I
want to use this reusable test step
block as it is
R there are two methods
either you can start creating step from
the beginning here
are you can reuse this and resolve the
reference
and modify it
so what I'll do I'm gonna reuse this
function I'm going to reuse this
checkout process as it is drag and drop
here
and bring this checkout process after
start checkout okay after start checkout
checkout process now
I can modify this
but when I modify this here it's gonna
modify your entire library because this
checkout process is coming from your
test step block
if I make any changes here right
everything is going to change here and
all the reference is going to change
basically your entire
test step in all the test cases is going
to change so now
because this checkout process is going
to change totally
I want to resolve the reference here
how
right click
and click on resolve reference
as soon as I click on resolve reference
what it happens the reference is now no
more with the library
this is now independent independent step
if you see here there is no suffix
reference it is an independent test step
now I can modify this test step
it is not going to impact your library
it is not going to impact your other
test cases also
so here under confirmation what is the
change that you need to do
sorry not under control under checkout
process the change is under payment
method credit card here I want to rename
this as
payment method
money order
correct I'm gonna select money order
so hence here instead of credit card I
want to select check our money order
correct and then click on continue let's
go over here
go to
genes
right
and then add 25 quantity I want to show
you on the web also to avoid the
confusion
okay
check out
and continue
payment method see here I am selecting
check our money order but not credit
card okay I selected that and then I'm
clicking on continue
so that is same and here payment
information is here
after this this modification is done
here payment information credit card we
have so this is not no more required
this I can this delete this entire step
here what is required
I need to capture a new module here so
let's go back to module because under
webshop whatever I captured here right
I have not captured the controls of the
screen this section payment information
section what I captured I only captured
credit card information see credit card
I have not captured this
so now I need to capture that how
right click
so right click here
click on scan click on application
now select the application that you want
to work on okay I want to work on
webshop right I want to capture all the
controls of that new section that is
appearing when I select money order
correct
so this is my webshop
click on scan
I'm gonna capture all the controls of
this new section
foreign
okay so here this is my basic view I
already explained how to scan in my
previous videos I suggest you guys to go
through those videos
I want to capture this
this message entire message table okay
capture this I want to capture this back
button click on this I want to capture
this continue button
and rename this table as
payment info
money order
table okay
done and I want to rename this entire
module as
web shop
webshop
payment
information
earlier we named it as credit card now
let me name it as money order
okay and one more thing if you see the
continue button is not uniquely
identified
correct that's why it's throwing as
error message okay here
so let's go to Advanced View
if you see
there are two ways you can make this as
unique by checking this visible because
this only one continue button is visible
on screen even though you have lot of
continue buttons but visibility is only
one
either you can just click on make unique
what it will do it's gonna check this
visible box done
selected item is now unique okay let's
go back to basic view now
you can do this and basic we also just
want to show you okay done
this is also done now save this module
as soon as I save this module
this new module will be saved and close
this
if you go back to your modules here the
new module is added the new module
payment information apart from payment
information credit card now you have
payment information money order also all
the controls are residing here
so now let's go back to your test case
here
instead of payment now I want to add
another test step here okay what is the
test step that I want to add if you
remember you can add the steps in the
both the ways right click
click on search and add step or click on
Ctrl t
which brings you your test tips okay all
the modules so now if you see let me
enter payment information if you see
here this is payment methods this is
payment yeah payment information money
order payment information credit card so
this is what we just now we created the
new module money order module I am
adding that module as a test step
done I added now if you see now as soon
as I click on continue it appears the
screen and here I need to select
continue I need not to select back or I
need not to capture this table so that's
why here I am gonna put X against
continue button
that's it
my new checkout process is now ready
I reused checkout process from my
library
but I resolve the reference
and I made some modifications to that
checkout process
by selecting the payment method as money
order instead of credit card and then by
removing the credit card details by
adding the payment information of money
order
done
now
what about after clicking on continue
and this verification of prices now
let's reuse the same verification of
prices from library
drag and drop to process
and this verification of prices comes
here after checkout you will have
verification of prices
and here under verification of prices
here
now there is a small change
if you go here
right here
here
the total e is not subtotal press
shipping
the total cost is subtotal plus shipping
plus payment additional information
earlier for credit card the your total
is just the subtotal and shipping cost
correct but now the Third
parameter is added so for that what we
need to do before I make it's very
important one thing you need to remember
guys before you make any changes you
have to resolve the references if you
don't resolve the references your entire
test step reusable test step in library
is going to change okay so that's the
reason because there is a change I want
to resolve the reference
and do modifications
so go to the verification of prices here
a simple small modification
car total
here
let me copy this math function here okay
let me copy this math function because I
want to reuse this later
okay okay here before I actually
calculate total I need to capture
my payment information so that's the
reason let me change this as a payment
information additional fee and I want to
validate if payment information
additional fee is
five dollars or not
this is five dollars right
five dollars
and verify this
is this a five dollars or not I am
verifying this
and here now I need to select total
now the total Math function changes what
is this apart from this 10 I need to add
5 also
this is done
so I am verifying total is not or not
change this to numeric
okay
that's it
let me just run this here okay I want to
make sure if it works fine or not
because it's already the screen is open
I can simply debug in this way okay
right click and run in scratch
and see what it will do
so it is verifying
your prices
it is taking lot of time that means
there might be something wrong
okay I think it's nothing is wrong I
think it's successful now
so now if you see the result right if
you see the result here go here
and see if the modifications you can see
or not okay if you see here apart from
subtotal we just added another parameter
called
payment method additional information if
you see here
your expected is y actually is why and
total
see your expected is 40 and actually is
40.
40 correct that means we are done so now
what we did I completed automating my
end-to-end test case
just like that
what I did I reused my
precondition as this I reused post
condition HDs I reused order products
capacities I reused star checkout as it
is I reused confirmation as it is I
reused verification of success as it is
the only changes I made is checkout and
verification of prices from my previous
test case
so now let me run this test case and see
how it works okay
let's log out this okay
log out
and close this
simply right click and run this new test
case that we created by using libraries
and reusable tested blocks
so now it should open your web
web application webshop
I think application seems to be very
slow
let's see what happens no not this
okay
I think let me close this
okay let me let me just go back here
okay let's go back to my test case again
if you see here the new test case
configuration we have to see let's see
if you see test configuration right we
have to add a test configuration for the
test case if you remember to add a
browser
let me add this new test configuration
new
test configuration
and take the browser
and select it as Chrome
now
save this
now let's execute the test case now
right click
I mean I already explained about these
configurations in my previous lesson
okay I will recommend you guys to go
through that session run in scratch
okay it opens your web browser
in Chrome now
and then click on login done
it enters username and password
click done login appearance and choose
blue jeans
it enters 25
and then shopping cart
agree now here payment method I have to
see
right the payment method it should
select check money order yes you
selected check money order and if you
see the check money order information
came and forty dollar
so that's correct order successful also
verified successfully he is logged out
and then
it's closed so everything is successful
so
see how easy it is
for us to automate any new test case if
you see here in the report these are all
your reusable functions
correct
and here also there yeah start checkout
process is not reusable function
okay
so
everything is success
so nothing is failure
right
hope you all understand the concept of
reusable tested blocks
and libraries how can we use while
automating your multiple test cases to
avoid the duplication of the work
you can reuse
entire
reusable functions it's kind of reusable
functions you create reusable functions
by using selenium right when you
automate the test cases in selenium you
create reusable functions right in the
same way you can create reusable tester
blocks and then you can reuse those
tested blocks in N number of test cases
so it cut Downs your
efforts and it takes very
uh less effort in automating the test
cases and it removes the duplication and
maintenance also very easy let's assume
under
login function okay when you are
actually logging in let's say your login
functionality during logging in so one
of the property got changed if you
change here
all the test cases whatever you are
referring from the precondition I mean
all the test cases
wherever this precondition is referenced
if all the test cases automatically gets
changed you need not to go to each and
every test case and change the property
so that's the maintenance also very easy
hope you all understand the concepts
it's very longer session uh but very
useful session okay if you have any
queries leave your queries in the
comment box I'll try to respond to your
queries thank you
[Music]